<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>My Two Cents</title>
        <link>https://rubenprofit.com/</link>
        <description>undefined</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 18:15:51 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en-US</language>
        <copyright>Copyright © 2021 Ruben Profit</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Awaited in Typescript]]></title>
            <link>https://rubenprofit.com/posts/awaited-type</link>
            <guid>awaited-type</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Dec 2021 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[New keyword drop!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
## Introduction

With the release of Typescript 4.5, a new utility type called `Awaited` was introduced. According to the documentation, this type "is meant to model operations like `await` in `async` functions, or the `.then()` method on Promise's - specifically the way that they recursively unwrap Promise's.". The goal of this article to attempt to unpack how this introduction can improve asynchronous programming.

**_Note: This article assumes you know the basic uses of typescript and promises in javascript._**

## The problem

Prior to the introduction of the `Awaited` keyword if you wanted to infer the return type of a promise after it resolved, you needed to `unwrap` the promise using the `infer` keyword. Below we will take a look at how that is done.

```Typescript
type Awaited<T> = T extends Promise<infer U> ? U : T; // custom Awaited type

const resolveTrue = Promise.resolve(true); // promise which resolves boolean

type promiseBoolean = Awaited<typeof resolveTrue>; // promiseBoolean is boolean!
```

As you can see in the above example, in order for us to get the `boolean` type resolved from the promise in `resolveTrue` we needed to first create an `Awaited` type which extended typescript's `Promise` type and *infer* the return type with `U` if it resolves and `T` if it doesn't resolve (ie. throws an error). Once typescript figures out the type of the promise, it will assign it to `U`. This is what typescript decribes as [inferring within conditional types](https://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/2/conditional-types.html#inferring-within-conditional-types). You can see where the need to **unwrap** the type was necessary. Our boolean was **wrapped** in a Promise like so `Promise<boolean>` but we needed to unwrap it using our *custom* `Awaited` type to bubble up the `boolean` type we wanted.

## The new way to do things

With the introduction of the `Awaited` type, we no longer need to use the above method and create a custom type to **infer** the type of resolved promise. Typescript does all the inference for us straight out of the box!

Here's an example of it in action:

```Typescript
const resolveTrue = Promise.resolve(true);

type promiseBoolean = Awaited<Promise<typeof resolveTrue>>; // promiseBoolean type is boolean!

const getFalse = (): promiseBoolean => {
    return Promise.resolve(false);
}; // TS won't throw error!
```]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Five tensor operations]]></title>
            <link>https://rubenprofit.com/posts/five-funcs-pytorch</link>
            <guid>five-funcs-pytorch</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A short introduction to PyTorch starting with 5 tensor methods.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
Last week I enrolled in [FreeCodeCamp's ZeroToGANs](http://zerotogans.com/) deep learning with PyTorch
course. The motivation behind doing so was mainly because of quarantine and wanting to learn something
new while being on lockdown.

As a software engineer mainly focused on app development, who by the way, barely completed college
level algebra and trig, I can say in total confidence that I have no clue what the hell I am getting
myself into or even if I have the capacity to complete it.

But, the cool thing about this course is that the instructors take a `code-first` rather than a
`math-first` approach in teaching the lessons and I think this works well for me because one thing
I can learn to userstand is code.

Now whether the `code-first` approach is the right way to get introduced into the space of machine
learning is something I won't get into and of course there are concepts that I would have to
learn in order to contribute anywhere effectively but the way I see it is:

> `I have to start somewhere right?`

So with all that said, this is by no means a hardcore introduction to data science. I won't be going
into things like **gradient descent**, **linear regression**, **neural networks** etc. because there
are plenty of authority figures who are better equipped to do so. Instead, what you'll find below
are **5 PyTorch methods** I found interesting that I think are a good way to get introduced to the
space starting with code.

## A little intro to PyTorch and torch.tensor

[PyTorch](https://pytorch.org/) is a python library built and maintained by Facebook, full of
programs to help facilitate building of deep learning projects.

PyTorch at its core processes multi-dimensional matrix called a
[tensor](https://pytorch.org/docs/stable/tensors.html). A tensor can contain **_integers_**,
**_floats_** and **\*booleans**.

To create a tensor in PyTorch, use the `torch.tensor` API likeso:

```Python
import torch

torch.tensor([1, 2, 3, 4])

# Output
tensor([1., 2., 3., 4.])
```

In the example above I created a one dimensional tensor with integers valued 1 - 4.

Outside of `torch.tensor`, the five methods I'll go over are:

-   torch.arange()
-   torch.split()
-   torch.stack()
-   torch.abs()
-   torch.add()

These are just methods I found that might be a good intro into PyTorch API but of course, if you want
to learn more check out the [documentation](https://pytorch.org/docs/stable/torch.html).

## Function #1 - torch.arange

Returns a one dimensional tensor with values from **_start_** to **_end_** incremented by **_steps_**.

```Python
# Example 1: 1-D tensor with size of 10 with steps of 1
torch.arange(10)

# Output
tensor([0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9])
```

Notice that the first value in our tensor starts with 0. If no **_start_** parameter is provided,
it defaults to **0**.

```Python
# Example 2 - More parameters
torch.arange(1., 2, .1, requires_grad = True)

# Output
tensor([1.0000, 1.1000, 1.2000, 1.3000, 1.4000, 1.5000, 1.6000, 1.7000,
1.8000, 1.9000], requires_grad=True)
```

Notice here the start and steps parameters are **float** points. We can also provide a range of
other parameters such as **_requires_grad_**, **_out_**, **_dtype_**, **_layout_** and **_device_**.

```Python
# Example 3 - breaking (to illustrate when it breaks)
length = 10
width = 5
torch.arange(length * width, step = 1, dtype = torch.get_default_dtype())

# Output
TypeError: arange() received an invalid combination of arguments
```

Be mindeful of how you organize your parameters. Correct way to write this would be like so:

```Python
torch.arange(start = 0, end = length * width, step = 1,
dtype = torch.get_default_dtype())
```

> torch.arange can be useful to create a one dimensional tensor of indices.

## Function #2 - torch.split

Splits the tensor into chunks. Each chunk is a view of the original tensor.

```Python
# Example 1 - Basic split
input_tensor = torch.tensor([50, 80, 10, 2])
torch.split(input_tensor, split_size_or_sections = 1)

# Output
(tensor([50]), tensor([80]), tensor([10]), tensor([2]))
```

Above we created a input tensor and used the split method to break our tensor data into equal
chunks of size 1.

```Python
# Example 2 - Split a tensor of ones, size 10, into chunks of at most size 2
x = torch.ones(10)
torch.split(x, 2)

# Output
(tensor([1., 1.]),
 tensor([1., 1.]),
 tensor([1., 1.]),
 tensor([1., 1.]),
 tensor([1., 1.]))
```

In the example above, first we created a tensor of **1**'s size 10. After which we use the split
method to split the tensor into chucks of seperate tensors with a size of atmost 2.

```Python
# Example 3 - breaking (to illustrate when it breaks)
y = torch.zeros([3, 3])
torch.split(y, 1, 3)

# Output
IndexError: Dimension out of range (expected to be in range of [-2, 1], but got 3)
```

We get this error **_IndexError: Dimension out of range_** when we attempt increase the dim size.
This causes an issue with the shape. Keep in mind the dimensions along which you want to split the tensor.

> torch.split is perfect when you need to split a Tensor into equal-size chunks!

## Function #3 - torch.stack

Concatenates sequence of tensors along a new dimension.

```Python
# Example 1 - Basic example
a = torch.ones([3, 3])
b = torch.zeros([3, 3])
torch.stack([a, b])

# Output
tensor([[[1., 1., 1.],
         [1., 1., 1.],
         [1., 1., 1.]],
        [[0., 0., 0.],
         [0., 0., 0.],
         [0., 0., 0.]]])
```

In the above example we create two seperated tensors using **_ones_** and **_zeros_**. After which
was concatenated into one tensor using the **_stack_** method.

```Python
# Example 2 - Stack two tensor on one dimension
c = torch.ones(5)
d = torch.zeros(5)
torch.stack([c, d], 1)

# Output
tensor([[1., 0.],
        [1., 0.],
        [1., 0.],
        [1., 0.],
        [1., 0.]])
```

In the above example we created another two tensors with the **_ones_** and **_zeros_** method.
This time when we concatenated them using the **_stack_** method we added an extra parameter for
our dimension we want to **_stack_** along.

```Python
# Example 3 - breaking (to illustrate when it breaks)
e = torch.ones(3)
f = torch.zeros(4)
torch.stack([e, f])

# Output
RuntimeError: stack expects each tensor to be equal size, but got
[3] at entry 0 and [4] at entry 1
```

We get the error above **_stack expects each tensor to be equal size_** because the shapes of
tensor **_e_** and **_f_** are not the same.

> torch.stack function is perfect when you need to concatenate two tensors of equal size.

## Function #4 - torch.abs

Computes the element-wise absolute value of the given input tensor.

```Python
# Example 1 - Basic example
ex_tensor = torch.tensor([-1, -2, -3])
torch.abs(ex_tensor)

# Output
tensor([1, 2, 3])
```

In the above example, first we created a tensor with all negative integers and passed that tensor
through torches **\*abs** which turned every element to a positive integer.

```Python
# Example 2
m = torch.tensor([1])
n = torch.tensor([2])
print('negative:', m - n)
torch.abs(m - n)

# Output
negative: tensor([-1])
tensor([1])
```

Similar to the first example, here we create two tensors using **_tensor_** method, after which we
run some arithmitic on both tensors which returns a negative integer but as you can see when we
pass that same expression to **_abs_** method it returns as positive.

```Python
# Example 3 - breaking (to illustrate when it breaks)
o = numpy.array([1, [-2]])
torch.abs(o)

# Output
TypeError: abs(): argument 'input' (position 1) must be Tensor, not numpy.ndarray
```

Make sure you pass a tensor as a argument to torch.abs unless it will throw the above error:
**_abs(): argument 'input' (position 1) must be Tensor, not numpy.ndarray_**.

> torch.abs is great when you want to work with all positive element in your tensor!

## Function #5 - torch.add

Adds the scalar other to each element of the input and returns a new resulting tensor.

```Python
# Example 1 - Basic example
p = torch.ones(10)
torch.add(p, 9)

# Output
tensor([10., 10., 10., 10., 10., 10., 10., 10., 10., 10.])
```

So in the above example we create a tensor of ones with size of 10 using **_ones_** method. Next we
pass our tensor of ones to the **_add_** method with an accumulator of 9 which takes each element
of our tensor and add 9 to it.

```Python
# Example 2
q = torch.randn(4)
r = torch.randn(1)
torch.add(q, r, alpha = 10)

# Output
tensor([17.4783, 17.0044, 17.4107, 19.7463])
```

In this example we create a tensor of random floats with size of 4. Next we create a tensor of a
random integer with size of one. Finally we add all the elements of **_q_** with **_r_** with a
scalar multiplier of **_10_**.

```Python
# Example 3 - breaking (to illustrate when it breaks)
s = complex(1, 1)
t = torch.zeros(1)
torch.add(t, s)

# Output
RuntimeError: Complex dtype not supported.
```

In the above example we create a complex number using the **_complex_** method. Then we create a
tensor of **_0_**'s with size of one and then attempt to add the element of our tensor to our
complex number. We get the error: **_Complex dtype not supported._** because only **_integers_** and
**_floats_** are supported in the **_add_** method.

> This function is great when you need to accumulate each element in your tensor by the same value.

## And that's about it

If you enjoyed this little intro I recommend checking out the rest of the documentation and also the
course. I'll link them below.

If you want to play around with the code, I've created a [Jupyter notebook](https://jovian.ml/unknouun/01-tensor-operations).
There you can run the examples I've written above. You can also fork it and play around with the API yourself if you so please.

## Reference Links

-   [Official documentation for `torch.Tensor`](https://pytorch.org/docs/stable/tensors.html)
-   [ZeroToGANs Lecture #1 PyTorch Basics - Tensors & Gradients](https://jovian.ml/aakashns/01-pytorch-basics)
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Interfaces and Classes]]></title>
            <link>https://rubenprofit.com/posts/interface-vs-class</link>
            <guid>interface-vs-class</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Contract, no EULA.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
So I've been interested [Typescript](https://www.typescriptlang.org/index.html) for a
while now because I kept seeing tweets like [these](https://twitter.com/kosalanuwan/status/1166276082451902465)
and I absolutely had to see what all the rage was about.

After trying it out I immediately saw all of the philosophical and technical benefits that it brings
to developing javascript applications. And over the course of me playing around with the language there were a lot
of things it brought to the javascript ecosystem that I was excited to use but for now I want to focus on just one,
[Interfaces](https://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/handbook/interfaces.html#introduction).

More specifically, the relationship between Interfaces and Classes and how and when to use them.

**_Note: I know Interfaces are already a thing in languages like C#, Java and other OOP languages.
This post is focused on use cases in Typescript. If you don't care feel free to hit me up with topics
you would like me to cover._**

According to the typescript documentation, an Interface is:

> A powerful way of defining contracts within your code outside your project.

To put it simply a Interface descibes _what_ a piece of code _must_ do.

Here's an example of a simple Interface:

```Typescript
interface BookInterface {
    title: string;
    author: string;
    pages: number;
    currentPage: number;
}
```

Now lets break this down. First we've initiated a _BookInterface_ interface with the keyword _interface_
and within our interface we describe properties called: _title_ and _author_ whose types must be strings;
_pages_ and _currentPage_ whose types _must_ be numbers. This tells any piece of code we have that
implements our Book interface that they must contain these variables and types.

But not only can we describe variables in an interface, we can also describe methods. Here's an example
extending our Book interface:

```Typescript
interface BookInterface {
    title: string;
    author: string;
    pages: number;
    currentPage: number;
    read(pgs: number): void;
}
```

In the above example we described a method called `read` whose type is `void` because we won't be
returning anything. The read method will just accept a parameter called `pgs` whose type must a
number and set the `currentPage` depending on how many pages read.

Since we created a Book interface, we exposed a few custom types now we can create a class that
follows the contract described by our interface, like so:

```Typescript
class Book implements BookInterface {
  public title: string;
  public author: string;
  public pages: number;
  public currentPage: number;
  public constructor(
    title: string,
    author: string,
    pages: number,
    currentPage: number = 0
  ) {
    this.title = title;
    this.author = author;
    this.pages = pages;
    this.currentPage = currentPage;
  }
  public read(pgs: number) {
    this.currentPage = pgs;
  }
}
```

Here we created a class called `Book` and by using the `implements` keyword we can have our class
subscribe to the contract of the `BookInterface`. Inside we give it all the properties, methodds
described in the interface and a `constructor` method to initialize an object. Now we have a class
that has custom types that are strictly enforced by our interface. This helps us have more
predictable and reusable code. We attached the **_public_** label to each item in order to avoid
calling the **_super()_** method.

**Note: Any class that implements an interface and does not include all of the properties will throw
the error:** **_Class incorrectly implements interface. Property is missing in type but required
in type._**

Now if we create a new instance of our `Book` we can see that all the custom types are there and checked:

```Typescript
const favoriteBook = new Book("Old Man's War", "John Scalzi", "351")
favoriteBook.read(10)
console.log(favoriteBook)
// Book { name: "Old Man's War", author: "John Scalzi", pages: 351, currentPage: 10 }
```

We can also use interfaces to create a custom type for initializing an object in our classes, like so:

```Typescript
interface BookConstructor {
  new (title: string, author: string, pages: number, currentPage: number): BookInterface
}

interface BookInterface {
    title: string;
    author: string;
    pages: number;
    currentPage: number;
    read(pgs: number): void;
}

class Book implements BookInterface {
  public title: string;
  public author: string;
  public pages: number;
  public currentPage: number;
  public constructor(
    title: string,
    author: string,
    pages: number,
    currentPage: number = 0
  ) {
    this.title = title;
    this.author = author;
    this.pages = pages;
    this.currentPage = currentPage;
  }
  public read(pgs: number) {
    this.currentPage = pgs;
  }
}

const favoriteBook = new Book("Old Man's War", "John Scalzi", "351")
favoriteBook.read(10)
```

Above, we created a new Interface because the last interface we created defined the instance methods
and properties and can't do both. Our new interface is very similar to the last interface we created
but also very different. After using the `interface` keyword to define a `BookConstructor` we then
set a `new` operator property with all the same parameters and types we need to construct our Book
class. The key here though is the `BookInterface` typing we assign the the new operator. This tells
typescript to run a check on the `BookInterface` to ensure that we have the necessary
parameters to create a new instance.

Using interfaces are an pretty good way to make sure that your classes play by the rules you want them to.

So now that we've covered the basics of how to create an interface and how they interact with classes,
let's look at a practical application of what we went over and put it together in a react app.

Lets say we wanted to create a simple web component that renders data about a book we are currently
reading and allows us to update the current page. We can use the same **BookInterface** we created
above and just pass it to a component like so:

```Typescript
import React, { useState } from "react";

interface BookInterface {
    title: string;
    author: string;
    pages: number;
    currentPage: number;
    read(pgs: number): void;
}

const BookComponent = (props: BookInterface) => {
  const [value, setValue] = useState<string>('')

  const handleChange = (e: object): void => {
    e.preventDefault();
    setValue(e.target.value);
  }

  return (
  <div>
    <p>{props.title}</p>
    <p>{props.author}</p>
    <p>{props.pages}</p>
    <p>{props.currentPage}</p>
    <input value={value} onChange={e => handleChange(e)} placeHolder='Current Page' />
    <button onClick={() => props.read(value)}>Current page</button>
  </div>
  )
}

export default App = () => {
  const [currentPage, setCurrentPage] = useState<number>(1)

  const read = (pgs: number): void => {
    setCurrentPage(pgs);
  }

  return (
    <div className="App">
      <BookComponent
        title="Clean Code"
        author="Ruben Profit"
        pages={4}
        currentPage={currentPage}
        read={read}
      />
    </div>
  );
}
```

And Voila!!! There it is. We created fully annotated React app using Typescript's interfaces

If you have any other questions or want to take a deeper dive into Typescript, I recommend checking
out the documentation. I'll link it below. There's also a really cool playground there that you can
checkout and test out typescript right in the browser.

## Reference Links

-   [Official documentation for Typescript](https://www.typescriptlang.org/docs/home.html)
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hello world!]]></title>
            <link>https://rubenprofit.com/posts/coming-soon</link>
            <guid>coming-soon</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I'll try and write a little here and there.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
I created this blog to write about things, in a space I have full control over.

So yeah expect more posts!

In the meantime, check out this [random wikipedia article](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Random).
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>